So, let us look at lists in
this algebraic datatype view.
So, for example, a list like '[1, 2, 3]',
as we have discussed on slides is actually
written with a lot of brackets
represented like this.
And we don't need those brackets.
Because we simply consider the colon, the 'cons'
constructor, as a right-associative operator.
And of course, we can also depict
this in some kind of tree form.
With such a right-slanted tree.
And this is all equivalent.
Okay.
And, of course, you can
always write it like this.
But if you want to do pattern-matching,
then we must take this perspective,
or it's useful to take this perspective,
if you want to have patterns like
checking for a non-empty list with
an arbitrarily long rest list.
Okay, so this was the outset.
Then we have this 'foldr' function,
and let's apply it with some
arguments 'f' and 'c', that
were these two arguments.
And let's say we apply this actually
to such a three-element list.
What will happen?
Well, of course, it's then 'foldr f c'
applied to something of this structure.
And if you look at the definitions of
the 'foldr' function, at the two cases,
then you will see it actually the
empty list will be mapped to 'c'.
And basically, for all intermediate colon 'cons'
constructors, the 'f' function will be inserted.
So, this call will ultimately
evaluate to something of this form.
(5 sec.)
Yes, that's what the recursive rule and then
the base case with the 'c' constant here tell
us. And then, of course, this gives you a good
indication of what the 'foldr' might be useful for.
For example, if you want to 'sum' a list,
then that's a very simple call of the 'foldr'
function, whereas the operator 'f' we use addition
as the base case, constant we use
0, and apply this to our list.
Yes, this will exactly mean in the example above,
that we would replace these three 'f's by +
and 'c' by 0.
And then it will, of course, compute
1 + 2 + 3 + 0, which
would be 6 in this case.
Okay, and there are many other functions,
of course, that can be defined with 'foldr'.
Very many of the interesting functions on lists.
So, for example, that might have occurred in the
exercises function, which basically
lifts the conjunction to a list.
So, given a list of Bools, it computes the
conjunction of all of them instead of simply
a binary conjunction with two Boolean arguments.
And well, how can we define the 'and' function?
Well, instead of writing a recursion, you would
simply say, well, it's a replication of 'foldr'
with what as the binary operator?
Well, the binary conjunction.
And what should be the base case of conjunction?
Well, the neutral element for conjunction is True.
So, if you're given a list of Bools, if
we evaluate this call, that really means
that we simply apply conjunction
between all elements.
And as the base case in this position, we
would use True, which ensures that if we build
conjunction over the empty list, then that is
True, as it makes mathematical and logical sense.
Okay, so these are some examples.
And I could really give
very many further examples.
And you will realize that if you
look at code in Haskell that often
works on lists, the predefined functions
are actually defined by our 'foldr'.
Then what I think I mentioned already is that
this picture should not tempt you to assume
that you will always have to or that in every
invocation, the whole structure would be computed.
That depends on the 'f'.
If the 'f', for example, at some
point doesn't need its right argument,
then, of course, only up to
that point you would compute.
Because this 'f' could, for example, compute
its output just from the 2, not needing the
right-hand side.
Then, of course, all these
calls wouldn't even be computed.
But that depends on the operators, right?
For the summation, for the '+' operator,
of course, we have to evaluate the whole
list because you need all elements.
Okay.
And then what's also a nice exercise
is to think about how you can
translate some function into this 'foldr' form.
And I will do this here for one
of the predefined functions.
So, the 'filter' function that we have
already discussed when we talked about
higher-order functions or in fact this
type polymorphically taking a predicate,
and a list, and returning a list.
And the idea was to remove all,
to drop all elements from the list
which don't satisfy this predicate.
Now, of course, you could start writing a
recursive definition for the 'filter' function.
But actually, you shouldn't have to do this.
Because there's always a good guess
that you can define it with 'foldr'.
Well, let's think about what
we would have to do for this.
So, we need 'foldr' that
needs some function argument.
So, we have to think about this.
But maybe we can already say what
the concept argument should be.
What is 'filter'?
With some predicate and the
empty list, the empty list.
So, that should go here.
And an interesting bit is what to put there?
Okay, how can we find out what to put there?
Well, one way is to look at what
would a recursive definition of
'filter' look like for the
case of a non-empty list?
So, what would you write if you
were to write a case like this?
What does 'filter p' do on a non-empty list?
Well, thinking about it, of course, it
depends on whether 'p' of 'x' is True or not.
So, this would be a case distinction.
If 'p' of 'x' is True,
then we should keep the 'x', and have a recursive
call of 'filter' with 'p' on the rest of the list.
And otherwise, we would not keep the
'x', and simply have this recursive call.
Okay, this is a very direct recursive definition.
And as such, it should really be equivalent to
some 'foldr' definition because 'foldr' basically
encapsulates and captures recursive definitions
on lists, which this 'filter' apparently is.
Okay, so what should this question mark here be?
This question mark place,
what should be put there?
Well, as often we can use the
lambda abstraction for this.
Well, what's the function
that you want to put there?
It's a function that, given
some current 'x' and something.
Yes, and the something will be
basically the recursive call.
Yes.
We call
that the second argument in this operator is
always what the 'foldr' computes on the rest list.
So, let's call this 'ys'.
Because it's not the 'xs'; it's some other
list, namely the result of the recursive call.
And what should we return?
Well, basically this right-hand side here,
but instead of having the recursive
calls here, we use our 'ys'.
Because in the 'foldr' we already have
as the second argument of our operation
the result of the recursive call.
So, basically, what we do is take
what we see above but abstract
these two recursive calls
into this new variable 'ys'.
So, what we would have here is
the same if call with 'p' on 'x'.
And if that is True, then we keep
the 'x' and use the 'ys' here.
And otherwise, we only use the 'ys'.
So, the point is that this variable here
now abstracts these recursive calls.
And if we put this really into this
place, then we have defined the 'filter'
function without explicit recursion
by simply using the 'foldr' function.
And similar strategies apply to
many recursive functions on lists.